Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Eleanor Newman Papers, 1974-1985 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Eleanor Newman papers 1974-1985 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company.
9.5 linear feet Extent: 6225 Items
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the largest and oldest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. Eleanor Newman was an Account Representative and Office Manager with JWT during the years 1976-1985. The Eleanor Newman Papers cover the years 1974-1985, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1979-1983, roughly the period during which Newman served as Office Manager of the J. Walter Thompson (JWT) Entertainment Group, and as Account Representative for the Health & Tennis Corporation account. The collection includes media plans, schedules, budgets, invoices, market research, proofs, tear sheets, photographs, conference call reports, memoranda and correspondence, and proposals related to the advertising campaigns of various JWT clients. Companies represented include Dentcare, Genesco, Circle Line Sightseeing Cruises, Jack La Lanne Spa, Vertical Club, Cover Girl, Freirich Meats, Beatrice Foods, Samsonite, Cable Shop, and Screenvision. Also included in the collection are media plans for the New York Arrows indoor soccer team, the 1981-1982 seasons of the New York City Opera, and several Broadway musicals including Mr. Lincoln, Really Rosie and Snow White.
RL.00732
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Eleanor Newman Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1993.
Biographical Note
Eleanor Newman graduated from Brooklyn College, majoring in English and Theater. Before joining JWT, she taught English to the gifted at the New York City Board of Education for six years.
Newman began working for the J. Walter Thompson (JWT) Company's New York office in 1976, first as secretary to the Director of Corporate Press. She was then promoted to Administrative Assistant, responsible for editing press releases; researching for annual reports; and writing articles for J. Walter Thompson News, the company newsletter. She also researched and wrote a major speech on the future of government advertising, presented at the American Association of Advertising Agencies convention in the spring of 1977. At the founding of the JWT Entertainment Group in September 1977, Newman was promoted to Office Manager, and made responsible for office services, hiring, and communication with the New York East Side Office. In 1978, she was promoted to Account Representative of the Entertainment Group. She subsequently handled the accounts of Caesars World, Radio City Music Hall, Ford's Theatre, Circle Line Sightseeing Cruises, and several Broadway shows. While at the Entertainment Group, she participated in the JWT Management Trainee Program, which culminated in a four-day seminar at Princeton University in 1980. In June 1981, Newman returned to the JWT East Side Office to become Account Representative for Health & Tennis Corporation, handling all the advertising for the forty-eight Jack La Lanne, Holiday Health Spa, and European Health Spa clubs, as well as the Vertical Club. She also handled Cable Shop responsibilities for Charm Step shoes on the Genesco account. In June 1982, she was promoted to Account Supervisor.
Newman also ghost-wrote articles for Penthouse, Playboy and the Chicago Tribune; and edited children's books on health, science, and Africa, in addition to a book on tennis and a biography of Elton John.
Collection Overview
The Eleanor Newman Papers cover the years 1974-1985, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1979-1983, roughly the period during which Newman served as Office Manager of JWT's The Entertainment Group, and as Account Representative for the Health & Tennis Corporation (later part of Bally Total Fitness Corporation) account. The collection includes media plans, schedules, budgets, invoices, market research, proofs, tear sheets, photographs, conference call reports, memoranda and correspondence, and proposals related to the advertising campaigns of various JWT clients. Companies and products represented include Dentcare, Genesco, Circle Line Sightseeing Cruises, Jack La Lanne Spa, Vertical Club, Covergirl, Freirich Meats, Beatrice Foods, Samsonite, Cable Shop, and PIAF/Screenvision. Also included in the collection are media plans for the New York Arrows indoor soccer team; the 1981-1982 seasons of the New York City Opera; and several Broadway musicals including Mr. Lincoln, Really Rosie and Snow White.
The collection is arranged into thirteen categories: General Files; Broadway; Cruise Tours; Dentcare; Fitness; Footwear; Freirich Meats; New York City Opera; Outdoor Advertising; Samsonite; Sports; Television; and Oversize Materials. The General Files include JWT directories, market research, office memoranda and forms, and correspondence relating to Mark Schoenfeld, Media Director at JWT Entertainment Group. Broadway files include media plans relating to the musicals Mr. Lincoln, Really Rosie, Snow White, Vaudeville Show, among others. The files on sightseeing cruise tours, Freirich Meats, the New York City Opera, Cable Shop and PIAF/Screenvision include advertising proofs, tear sheets, television and radio advertising schedules, and media plans. The Footwear files include proposals, advertising copy, proofs, media plans and market research for Covergirl and Genesco's Charm Step and Easy Street lines of shoes. Samsonite, the largest category of files in the collection, includes several booklets of research findings on the 1980s luggage market, marketing proposals and recommendations, and advertising tracking studies. The Outdoor Advertising files includes photographs, market research and correspondence related to billboard, bus and bus shelter advertising of Broadway musicals in New York City. Oversize Materials consist of large-format items removed from other series and housed separately.
Many of the marketing proposals and market research findings arrived in binders labeled with a title sheet or subject headings. Items were removed from binders, and original titles were used. Several sections were removed from their respective series into a separate oversize box.
Subject Headings
Newman, Eleanor; J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson Company. Cable Shop; J. Walter Thompson Company. Entertainment Group; J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office; Bally Total Fitness Corporation; Beatrice Foods Company; Circle Line Sightseeing Cruises; Dentcare Delivery Systems, Inc.; Genesco, Inc.; J. Freirich Foods, Inc.; New York City Opera; Samsonite Corporation; Screenvision Cinema Network, LLC; Advertising -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Advertising executives; Advertising executives -- United States; Dental care -- Marketing; Fitness industry -- New York, N.Y.; Footwear industry -- United States; Luggage industry -- United States; Marketing research; Marketing -- United States; Music theatre -- United States; Advertising, Outdoor; Television advertising -- United States; Women in the advertising industry; Memoranda; Photographs; Proofs; Proposals; Tear sheets; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections of J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) Archives: Ted Wilson Papers; Account Files Collection; Review Board Records; Bertram Metter Papers; and New York Office Records. Materials relating to women in advertising may be found in the JWT Rena Bartos Papers; JWT Nan Findlow Papers; JWT Lois Gaeta Papers; and the JWT Sidney Ralph Bernstein Company History Files. Materials relating to JWT's Cable Shop may be found in the JWT Chicago Office Non-Proprietary Research Reports; the JWT Publications Collection; and the JWT Newsletters Collection. Materials relating to the JWT Entertainment Group may be found in the JWT Edward G. Wilson Papers.
- General Files, 1979-1982 and undated, (1 Box)
  Includes memoranda, correspondence, handwritten notes, and printed information relating to the operation of J. Walter Thompson Company accounts and the JWT subdivision The Entertainment Group. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Directories, undated (Box 1)
  - Media market research, rates and schedules, 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Media plan drafts and correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Memoranda and notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Rebate information, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Schoenfeld (Mark) correspondence, 1979 (Box 1)
- Broadway, 1979-1981, (1 Box)
  Includes proposals, schedules and purchase orders for television, radio and print advertising of selected Broadway shows. Original folder titles were maintained. Arranged alphabetically.
  - General media plans, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Mr. Lincoln
    - Media schedules, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Proofs, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Purchase orders, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Radio and television production charges, 1980, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Really Rosie media plan, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Snow White media plan, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Various productions media plans, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Vaudeville Show media plan, 1980 (Box 1)
- Cruise Tours, 1979, 1981, (1 Box)
  Includes invoices, financial estimates, press kits, market research, proofs, marketing campaign proposals, tear sheets and media schedules for the sightseeing cruise companies Circle Line and Cruise Lines. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Circle Line (Box 1)
    - Billing and invoices, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Financial estimates, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Office memoranda, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Press kit, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Proofs, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Proposals, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Tear sheets, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Television production estimates, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Television and radio schedules, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Cruise Lines, media data, 1981 (Box 2)
- Dentcare, 1980-1981, (1 Box)
  Includes financial estimates, invoices, media proposals, proofs and printed material relating to the marketing of the dental company Dentcare. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Billing estimates and correspondence, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Invoices, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Media plans, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Monthly Billing Reports, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Proofs and flyers, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Yellow pages service orders, 1981 (Box 2)
- Fitness, 1981-1983, (1 Box)
  Contains conference call and meeting reports, financial reports, print media proposals relating to the Health & Tennis Corporation (HTC). Also includes materials relating to HTC subsidiaries the Jack La Lanne Spa and the Vertical Club, such as media campaign proposals, rates, schedules, memoranda, correspondence, model head shots, tear sheets and television buy invoices. Original folder titles were maintained. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Health & Tennis Corporation
    - Account shift plan, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Call reports, Los Angeles office, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Call reports and meeting reports, New York, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Gross sheets, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Print campaign, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Status report, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Jack La Lanne Spa
    - Campaign, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Memoranda and correspondence, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Radio campaign proposal, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Television buys, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Television proposal, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Vertical Club
    - Copy strategy, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Media schedules, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Model head sheets, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Proofs, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Prospective publications, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Rates, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Tear sheets, 1981 (Box 3)
- Footwear, 1981-1983, (1 Box)
  Includes advertising campaign plans, conference call reports, project lists, tear sheets, product design information and market research relating to the footwear market, and particularly to the companies Cover Girl and Genesco, including Genesco subsidiary branches of Charm Step and Easy Street. Original folder organization and titles were maintained. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Cover Girl
    - Advertising Platform, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Call Reports, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Media plans, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
    - Print advertising, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Project lists, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Trade media and direct mail, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Genesco
    - General files--Production charges, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Charm Step, 1982
      - Call reports (Box 4)
      - Campaign materials (Box 4)
    - Easy Street, 1982
      - Advertising platform (Box 4)
      - Call reports (Box 4)
      - March project list (Box 4)
      - Media plans (Box 4)
      - Shoe designs (Box 4)
      - Tearsheets (Box 4)
    - Men's Footwear Review, 1982, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Freirich Meats, 1982, (1 Box)
  - Proposal for marketing campaign, 1982 (Box 4)
- New York City Opera, 1981-1982 and undated, (1 Box)
  Series includes schedules, campaigns, budgets and buy invoices for television, radio and print advertisements of the 1981 and 1982 seasons of the New York City Opera, including Operetta plans from 1981. Also includes memoranda and correspondence relating to these campaigns. Original folder organization and titles were maintained, except for media plans. These were separated into seasons and made into a Media Plan sub-category. Large-format materials were removed to Oversize Materials. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Campaign proposal, 1982 Spring (Box 4)
  - Media plans
    - 1981 Spring (Box 4)
    - 1982 Spring [Items removed to Oversize Materials, Box 8.] (Box 4)
    - 1982 Fall [Items removed to Oversize Materials, Box 8.] (Box 4)
  - Media schedules and budget, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Office memoranda, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Operetta plans, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Proofs, undated (Box 4)
  - Radio and television buys, 1982 (Box 4)
- Outdoor Advertising, 1979 and undated, (1 Box)
  Includes market research, schedules, contracts and photographs relating to billboard and bus shelter advertising in New York City. Most of the materials pertain to the advertisments of JWT client TDI. Also includes photographs of billboards in Times Square. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Market research, undated (Box 5)
  - TDI
    - Contracts, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Photographs, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Schedules, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Times Square billboards, 1979 (Box 5)
- Samsonite, 1974-1985 and undated, (2 Boxes)
  Series contains financial records, five-year reviews, budgets, market research, marketing proposals, model release forms, and correspondence relating to Samsonite campaigns during the years 1976 to 1984. Includes a subseries of agenda packets for presentations on luggage market research, and materials relating to the 1982 "Survivor" advertising campaign. Also contains two folders of correspondence between JWT and the Leo Burnett Advertising Company of Chicago. Original folder organization and labels were maintained. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Files in storage, undated (Box 5)
  - Financial records, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Leo Burnett Advertising Company correspondence, 1984 [Items removed to Oversize Materials, Box 8.], 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Market research
    - Ad tracking study, 1983 (Box 5)
    - Information planning base, 1976-1977, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Luggage Advertising Review, 1982-1983, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Luggage Market in the 1980s, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Point of View Regarding the Future of the Luggage Market, 1976 (Box 5)
    - Preliminary Discussion of Samsonite Research Needs, 1976 (Box 5)
    - Proposal for Monitoring the Short Term Impact of Alternative Spending Levels, 1983 (Box 6)
    - Proposal for Strategic Research of the Luggage Market, 1976 (Box 6)
    - Proposal for Strategic Study of the Luggage Market, 1981 (Box 6)
    - Qualitative Study on the Luggage Market, 1982 (Box 6)
    - Segmentation study, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Model release forms, 1976-1984 (Box 7)
  - Presentations
    - Advertising program, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Advertising recommendations, 1984-1985, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Awareness tracking, 1983 wave (Box 7)
    - Beatrice Foods proposal, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Five-year review, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Five-year review, media delivery, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Information summary for strategic review board, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Issues and concerns for 1985, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Objectives
      - 1981 February, 2 copies (Box 7)
      - 1981 March (Box 7)
    - Strategic and copy development, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Strategy, 1979 (Box 7)
    - T-plan, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Traditional Select Opportunity, undated (Box 7)
  - Strategic plan, 1974, 1979, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Survivor campaign, 1982 (Box 7)
  - Television and radio commercials, 1983 list (Box 7)
- Sports, 1981-1982 and undated, (1 Box)
  Includes media plans for the indoor soccer team, the New York Arrows, and for the televised series, the World Games. Original folder titles were maintained. Arranged alphabetically.
  - New York Arrows media plan, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - World Games media plan, undated (Box 7)
- Television, 1981-1982, (1 Box)
  Includes schedules, cost estimates, scripts, campaign proposals, tracking and focus group research for the television shopping network Cable Shop. Also includes market research and media plans related to PIAF/Screenvision, and media research data for RCTV. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Cable Shop (Box 7)
    - Estimates, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Focus groups
      - Men, 1982 (Box 7)
      - Women, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Genesco campaign, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Management overview, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Original scripts, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Pilot test review, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Proposal, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Schedules, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Tracking research, 1982, (4 folders) (Box 7)
  - PIAF/Screenvision
    - Ideal Audience, The Power to Influence It, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Market analysis, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Media plans, 1981 (Box 7)
  - RCTV media data, 1981 (Box 7)
- Oversize Materials, (1 Box)
  Comprises large-format files removed from elsewhere in the collection.
  - General files (Box 8)
    - Managers meeting agenda, 1982 August (Box 8)
  - Fitness--Health & Tennis Corporation
    - Jack La Lanne Spa, media schedules, 1982 (Box 8)
  - New York City Opera, media plans, 1982 (Box 8)
  - Samsonite
    - Leo Burnett Advertising Company correspondence, 1984 (Box 8)
    - Proofs, undated, (9 folders) (Box 8)